[Music]
okay well we're here
um as friends
to reinvent your friendship or
philia um to use the greek word yeah
which is a deeper word that means you
know i think it means sacred friendship
uh in some sense yep and um
i wrote an article a while a long time
ago about about the subject and i
rewrote it i sent it to you guys but i
i think the the um the thesis
is is really that that friendship is is
not a commodity
uh that it's sacred that it's a
vulnerable thing that it's it's risky
it's it's not something cheap that can
be
you know uh um bought and sold on social
media
and and uh so i tried to i tried to
write down my article in ten sentences
but
the first sentence was uh friendship is
how we steal the culture
um um because that sort of makes sense
to me would you would you agree with
that john because you're the originator
of that phrase
um i think so um i mean
so for me philia captures
two terms um that we should maybe try to
bring into
discussion together it obviously
captures fellow
it captures friendship like you said uh
but uh
the the invocation of the stealing of
the culture um
also invokes the model i was using which
was uh
christianity in the period of late
antiquity and then the crit
well then the notion i want to bring in
is the christian notion of fellowship
uh where fellowship um right is
not it's not the same it's not to be
identified with friendship but nor can
you keep it distinct
um and philia covers both i think philia
is the love that emerges out of
and is in the care for things that are
self-organizing
that are living it that are living and
and so the christian notion of
fellowship was the philia that emerged
out of and sustained the body of christ
right uh the church as the body of
christ so and and the med and
of course bodies are self-organizing
they're auto-poetic they're
self-making living things and and so
philia
uh and in so far as it was associated
also with um
wisdom is that there's the sense of the
community like the school
right uh because pythagoras coins the
term and he simultaneously founds a
community a school
right where so there's fellowship out of
the school emerges
right a kind of love right that uh
it emerges out of the community but it
also sustains the community as its
organizing principle as its logos and
then it it is but it's not just
self-organizing it's like a living thing
it is directed towards something it is
the philia for sophia
the the the love of wisdom and so
i i think that uh if we could bring
um that notion of fellowship
the pythagorean christian notion if
you'll allow me that
into aristotle's notion of friendship as
the idea of a suke in two bodies
so that the bodies get a self-organizing
principle a shared life
between them like the bodies of the
people like the people in the church
yeah i think there's a profound uh
discourse that we could open up there
between that aristotelian idea
and and the pythagorean christian idea
of sort of friendship fellowship
yeah so i will share the fellowship is
about a quest
too which that's what yes yeah the
fellowship of the ring i'm thinking
about the fellowship of the ring and
it's a quest so that's that's another
dimension uh of friendship which i i
hadn't considered
and that's very much within the
pythagorean tradition because for
pythagoras
you were on a quest for wisdom literally
a soul flight towards wisdom
um and so and that's where that he
really gave
uh mythological teeth to the uh notion
of wisdom as
a a profound kind of self transcendence
so the questing ella i
thank you for bringing that out andrew
that's exactly also intended
in things like the fellowship of the
ring and so
i've been thinking a lot about you know
eros as the love that
comes out of and uh nurtures emergence
by leah as the love that emerges out of
and nurtures self-organization
and then agape is the love that um that
that comes from
and and helps sustain the way things
emanate
uh you know and so i've been really
playing with sort of
the metaphysical correlations of the
three kinds of love as well
and so that's that's the final thing i
want to say
um and then i'll let you guys respond is
so i'm trying to bring the pythagorean
christian the aristotelian
and then this final notion you might
call it the uh
the neoplatonic or dialectic of seeing
philia
as the important uh uh mediation
between eros and agape as well
okay great yeah i was sort of thinking
that this conversation
we could focus on philia maybe but
but uh if if we if we bring in all three
that that's okay
as well of course because because
everything is very interconnected
well i do want to focus on finally but
what i'm saying is i think there's these
three
aspects to it and i think they're all
related the aristotelian aspect the
pythagorean christian aspect
and what we might call the dialectic or
neoplatonic aspect
of it great
i'm glad you brought in the um the the
aristotelian notion of the shared the
shared
tsuke because that's something that then
is developed i think further developed
in christianity augustine i think uses
some of the same language
can you tell us that's what suke means
in this sense
i see okay yeah it also it sort of
covers
soul and mind it's in the word
psychology psyche
and it also means that about you which
is self-moving
so it also it's part of this self-moving
self-organizing
so it's sort of soul and psyche mixed
together as a dynamic principle of some
kind yeah
yeah basically okay and that that maybe
two opens the door to add one more
dimension to what you've just said john
which is that
to understand friendship authentic
friendship and maybe later on we can
also talk about maybe make some
distinctions between authentic and
inauthentic friendship
because i think that would be probably a
very fruitful territory
for us to venture into because our the
landscape is rife with
inauthentic friendship um and i think
it's very important for us to qualify
what we mean by that
but i think that the there's a uh a
dimension of
socratic self-knowledge in the pursuit
of genuine and reciprocal authentic
friendship
because friendship authentic friendship
i think makes manifest
the the
the realization that one cannot know
without
being known in return the project of
knowing
and being known are conjoined projects
and
the conjunctive nature of those of those
projects is something that is only
realized
in deep friendship in philia so
couldn't you put the two together then i
mean
what i'm thinking of is sorry to
interject but maybe you can riff on this
then
right the idea that you know the friend
friends are each other's divine double
um because that you get the sense of the
shared suitcase because the divine
double
is right the same suitcase in two bodies
or two locations
and there's an aspirational relationship
to them yes but you also get the
pythagorean quest
right the aspirational quest um between
two
yes yes exactly the friend the friend
becomes a symbolic vow
by whom you pursue your authentic self
right
and um and to whom you pursue your
authentic self too right because you're
also affording them
the same thing that's right that's right
because the the if i can use the you
know
that we often use especially when we're
talking about dialogue we often use the
the fire metaphors the metaphors of the
campfire and so maybe to reintroduce
that a little bit
the the light that is kindled in the
virtue of friendship is the light by
which you uncover
yourself right and without which you
cannot
uncover yourself um and so i think that
so understanding
the project of self-knowledge almost in
a meiodic way of of uncovering
recollectively
that of yourself which is not yet known
to you
there seems to be a deep necessity of
friendship in the cultivation of that
project
um and then the other thing i might
throw in too you know you i remember you
said something actually to me john
a long time ago and then i read
something similar i think in
in seneca um seneca has a has an epistle
on friendship
and and he says something quite
beautiful it's very similar to something
you once said to me
and then proceeded to live out
incidentally um
which is that the the a friend
is one against whose death
you stake your life and
now we could we could think of that
literally of course but we could also
think of death as
the the soul's despair and i to me
that's a little bit more of a helpful
way of thinking about it so i might say
something like
friend a friend is what is a soul
against whose despair we stake our life
and there is a sense in which a real
the cultivation of a real friendship
when you when you
you're you're at a real friend
a real friend is someone
in whose fate you implicate yourself
yeah a soul who in whose fate you become
implicated
voluntarily implicated and who brings
you uh who lifts you up from despair
at the same time right yes with whom you
despair
and with whom you recover and then you
also just stare from it
yeah so there's yeah that's so beautiful
yeah so you're picking up on the one of
the essential features of
the the suitcase is that the
self-knowing the self-caring
and then that gets extended uh through
another person
um that's right they become conjunctive
they become conjunctive and that i think
that also serves maybe to to connect up
to the insight that
um in in a way that that friendship has
that mediatory function between
you know the the knowing and the being
of oneself and the knowing and being of
of of the world writ large right the
countenance of one and the countenance
of the world
are are reconciled or resolved
in the relation of friendship yeah
because the uh so you're saying
something like the friendship
is where we get the second person
perspective that mediates between the
first and the third person perspectives
that's right and forms the bind and
there and thereby forms the religio the
binding
and it's an interesting thing because
it's always perplexed me
um phenomenologically
uh because obviously linguistically
conceptually we have the first
and second and third person forums we
that's that's indisputable
and and we're picking up on something
that has some sort of phenomenological
functional basis i get that but
like as a phenomenological exercise it's
very easy like
like if you're sitting in meditation for
example you can adopt the first person
perspective sort of
this here now or you can adopt the third
person's perspective no one nowhere no
when
but what is it like what is it you're
doing when you move into the second
person
perspective it's this weird stereoscopic
thing where you're
looking out through your eyes but you're
also looking
back through the through the the the
beloved other
right and yet those are somehow fused
into
a unified perspective the second person
perspective
is a very odd like i'm trying to i'm
trying to get us to
remember before we were in dentio the
strangeness
and the oddness uh in comparison to the
first person
perspective and the third person
perspective the second person
perspective is very very odd indeed
very very odd indeed and i wanna i wanna
see how that
the the weirdness of the second person
perspective the way
the way it binds the two others together
so there's a way in which it binds
the first and the third person
perspective as you said chris and then i
want to bring back what i was saying
there's something about friendship
fellowship the way it binds us
into something that takes on a life of
its own right so
a friendship right a friendship isn't
there's a sense in which both people and
that's the analogy to
dear logos a friendship draws people
like
a friendship takes on a life of its own
and it leads both
of its members or more than two people
right there's joy there's more you know
friendships larger than that
right but it leaves them place it like
it takes on a life of its own and
it takes that's what happened i mean
that's the myth of the fellowship of the
ring
they like the holy spirit it's the yes
right
the third yeah
why do you say it's weird john what's
the weirdness
is it is it just because um because if
you're if you you could
well you're this isolated let's say
um atomistic if you like if you're
meditating
and and you don't have that sense
perhaps it becomes a sterile exercise um
it could
and if you and if you don't have and
else and and you you're just
there has to be this this this
devotional sense
in some sense to to another another
principle higher principle it could be a
person or not otherwise i think
you're stuck in the i it relationship
and you don't get into the vow
um i i i acknowledge all of that and
what i meant what i meant and weird is
uh let me try and articulate it in terms
of
the grammar of our assumed metaphysics
okay
first person perspective max onto
subjectivity
third-person perspective maps onto
objectivity
what does a second-person perspective
map onto
yeah neither and both
and yeah you know yeah well that's what
i've been trying to get with this notion
of transactivity transactivity yeah
yeah and so friendship friendship is one
of our most powerful ways
of inhabiting and disclosing the trend
and
transactivity as something of equal
standing
and i think even more primordial
standing because of the way it mediates
and grounds
subjectivity and objectivity and i think
because
our culture and this is one of the
things i've been arguing for quite a
while right
because our culture doesn't speak about
transactivity
at all very much i think it it it is
largely
at its metaphysical depths incapable of
speaking about the grounding of
friendship
okay so we have the sacred notion of
friendship which
we've been explored and then we have the
profane
uh aspect of friendship which is you
know
everywhere today it's it's it's been
reduced to its
to a commodity it's been reduced to a
kind of casual notion
where everybody you associate with is is
your friend
on some level and it's it's become
something that people you know facebook
makes
billions of dollars you know on this
notion a
friend so so um can you can you explore
those book
can you guys explore those two aspects
and the difference between them
but i think it follows on what i was
just saying i think because we don't
uh because we've lost the connections
between
friendship and fellowship and because we
we've lost
the the metaphysical home in transit
activity for friendship
i i think i think it's very difficult
for us to get to the depths
of friendship and friendship becomes
just a casual relationship where you
kind of get your rocks off with your
i think friendship you're not building
towards this something or
you're not creating a symphony together
or
something like that you know yeah i i
mean
i i mean when you when you don't have a
grammar that takes you into ontological
depth perception you're going to
you're going to degrade and default to
the lowest common denominator
and what is the lowest common
denominator well it's it's human
association
we associate and we use that we used to
have more fine-grained distinctions
so i mean i i understand what chris
meant by inauthentic but
what i mean is we used to have authentic
categories that were non-friendship
categories
there were there were literally your
associates acquaintances
there were your acquaintances and there
were your associates and there were your
colleagues
and these were not understood to be
friends nor should they be friends
and then we got the weird sitcom thing
that happened where now everybody is
your family
and everybody is your friend and it's
like well no
i don't want that because that removes
the distinctness
of friendship i i want people that are
good colleagues
and i will appreciate them as good
colleagues but i don't want them to be
my
friend and i want people who are my
acquaintances
and and and and we and we we even
invented a new term
um in modernity or recently that i
thought captured a
another category that you had the buddy
and the buddy isn't a friend and that's
one of our biggest mistakes
the buddy is somebody that you do fun
things with
they're your buddy like they're your hey
there's my rollerblading buddy
right and that and that's mine because
again
right we're not we're not trying to
legislate the
relationships but what we've done again
because we
lack the ontological death perception is
all those distinctions have collapsed
and that is adulterated adulterated and
confused our understanding
so that we have this well as you said it
this profane
notion of friendship because it is a
notion that it's
muddied and equivocal and has lost
the important intelligibility that all
those distinctions gave us
if i can be like uh bring this down to
something like uh
you know for for men for example
friendship is
is is beer and and football you know and
for
and whereas it used to be church um
you know yeah in a sense yeah i i don't
go to church
and and i i don't want to become a
christian but i prefer the church
thing to the beer in football you know
the alcohol
and and and sports uh
thing uh just just almost that's like
the masculine aspect of friendship
because it's interesting because like
philia it means brotherhood doesn't it
doesn't yeah
of course we should we should include
sisterhood in the notion of course
of course texas yes but but uh but
brotherhood
uh you know this notion of brotherhood
um
is quite it has been has been reduced to
that
or yeah i mean i i i
you know there's people that i can sit
like
well before covet i used to do
role-playing games and you know you have
your role-playing
buddies yeah like you go in there and
you have this fun thing you do it
together and it's great right
but that's that's it it's organized
around
the the pleasure of a shared activity
and of course you know
drinking beer with somebody at a
football game is an instance of that
but that's not the same thing as like
fellowship like you're saying when you
go to church
and what happens i mean it's an archaic
term now
i but when i was growing up and in
church we used to use the term
edification
like edifice like building a building we
were engaged in the project of building
each other up in the christian life yeah
yeah so one of the things so taking what
both of you have said and maybe just
viewing it from then from a slightly
different vantage one
thing then one property that we can use
to distinguish one kind from the other
first as you said john that one is what
we might call a real or authentic
friendship
again not a definition just a property
is that it is not
contingent on a shared context that is
then repeated and reproduced
it is it rather than being reproduced by
a shared context it is it in and of
itself
reproductive of then the context in
which you can share the time
and so to me that gives the feeling that
what we when we say real or authentic
friendships
they do not rely on the contextual of a
predetermined world
to find relevance and significance
rather they create and unfold between
themselves
that shared context and world that then
becomes enveloping of all other things
oh that's good that's why that's why
when you're in the presence of a real
deep friend it truly does not matter
what you're doing
yeah you can sit with them on a log in
the woods
and that's enough that's enough it it
and to me that's the difference
so that's that's one thing and then the
other is that up on that
that's really worse i find that's
brilliant i won't talk a lot i won't say
very much
i think that's brilliant i think you've
articulated and
extrapolated what i was trying to convey
with this idea of the love that emerges
and cares for
something that has a life of its own
that's self-organizing i think what you
just said there was brilliant and
articulated it perfectly
yeah right also we can bring that to the
level of of
you know what i said in the beginning of
culture you know uh uh still
just individual uh it's like that's how
that's how that's how we create
a culture that is living rather than a
culture that is just based on in these
dead
institutional forms that's right that's
right exactly
yeah i think that's exactly right um
and and then the second thing is that
and they're obviously they're
they're interrelated is that they're
the the i'm going to put this in scary
quotes but the real friendship
is is infinitely dissimilar from all
other friendships
it is incomparable to any other it is
it is a co it is a kind and not an
instance right
it is not comparable to any other
freight so you know andrew you were
talking about you know you have your
people that you go to the pub with and
drink beer and watch football
and um there is a degree to which
all of those friendships are similar
because of their shared context
and it is the dissimilarity of that
singular friendship that marks it and
you know it if it is if it is a kind
unto itself
rather than an instance of a kind of
friendship i think that also is one way
of of telling the difference
but that like you said that follows
perfectly
from the from the previous point because
if it is a thing that
that is autonomous literally it creates
that it creates the no
moss for itself it creates the laws and
the standards for itself
because it is a auto it is a self-making
thing
a self-organizing thing with a life of
its own it's going to have
that uniqueness to it right that's
exactly it has to be the case
i would argue i think i think it's i
think it's not just a related sequence i
think there's an implication maybe even
an
entailment from the first point into the
second point that's a good point
yeah yeah i think you're right i think
you're exactly right yeah they're not
they're not just
they're not just two independent
properties but they are they are
one one is implicated by the other
exactly
implied by the other i mean to say yeah
and that would then mean right why it's
so
yeah i mean think about how that then
goes back to your previous point
maybe these the points are cons there's
a consolation forming
because in so far i mean i'm doing this
whole course now on the nature and
function of the self
and one of the functions of the self is
it's supposed to pick out uniqueness
right um so insofar as i share
properties
with other people those aren't the
properties that pick out myself
and there's problems there with that i'm
not right
but it's some idea that in some way
yourself
is that about you which individuates you
um
and and which picks you out um
from other persons um gives you what we
call a personal identity a biographical
identity etc
etc um and and we we sometimes transfer
that to
objects like works of art have that kind
of self
because right any any painting other
than the original
night watch by rembrandt is a fraud
right and so
right because it's a unique language
right i mean
if you have a deep real friend you
generate a unique language together
that's a great point andrew it's nobody
else's language right
right you know and what i'm saying is
that unique language feeds back into the
point chris was making about
socratic self-knowledge it literally
gives you the language by which you
bespeak yourself
by which you can carve out and
individuate yourself
right in which you can write ah so it's
a unique language but it's also the
language that allows you to communicate
outside of
of of or outside that's right
that's why you speak that's why you
speak more fully and more truly when you
speak
into the ear of your friendship yes
right because the ear of your friendship
right which we might call that third
entity the the spirit or the geist as as
you and i have called it john
when you speak into the ear because its
ear is more resonantly comprehending
the tenor of your speeches the the
breadth and the compass of your speech
suddenly grows
it's it's the totality of its reference
grows more encompassing
because its capacity for comprehension
is that much more you're speaking into
an entire world when you speak into an
authentic friendship and so therefore
your your
your your um you know your voice that
your vocality takes on a resonance the
logos takes on a resonance and is able
to self-multiply in that heracliton way
that it is not otherwise able to do
that's the fecundity
of of the world that's created between
two authentic friends
right and so what what i'm saying about
that is
like they're they're i'm trying to get
the
sort of the resonance there and i like
in speaking to the depths i have to
speak
from my depths and in speaking from my
depths
i actually make myself into a new kind
of self and this is the way in which i
think the cell
the suke is shared between two people
right that process of self definition
is being shared in some resonant fashion
between two individuals and it's to
realize
and you'll like this chris because this
i've been reading a lot of uh
uh what's his name the guy who wrote the
book on uh is it fuller
on on dialogue says midwifery talking
about socrates and jesus yes stephen
faller right yeah stephen fuller
and he's done a section on socratic uh
irony as seen by kirker guard
and so there's this kirk guardian point
about the
friendship is a place in which we can
deeply realize
and i'm loading lots of connotation into
the word realize
that the self is inherently dialogical
yeah
yes yes yes exactly or and then to riff
on that and put it even
just in another pithy way john the the
the speaking between friends is how we
learn to speak with ourselves
yes exactly and that that's uh i was
just teaching a lesson
um in the on the at the saturday saying
that we've gone through
you know epicurus who taught that the
greatest virtue of course is friendship
and then we've moved into the stoics and
antisthenes you know coming out of
socrates
what did you learn from socrates well i
learned how to converse with myself
but he doesn't mean we he means we
replace that stupid babble we do on our
head all day long
with something like socratic dialogue
with in the affordance and the
aspiration to wisdom
and yet and that only in friendship is
that possible that
speaking to the depths from the depths
it's like there's something
there um and like i said i i think it's
unreasonable i think it's deeply
unreasonable to expect that to have that
those mini deep and unique to pick up on
your point chris
deep and unique living relationships
with very
many people yeah that's very hard you
only have a few that's the other thought
yeah i was saying like you only have a
few
friends in the sense we're we're talking
here yeah maybe a hand have a lot it's
not a it's a quant
it's a qualitative not a quantitative
thing exactly it's marked up your 5 000
friends on facebook
by any means or it's not even just like
a lot of people that you know
it's it's it's like it's a small amount
of
people and and crucially to your point
andrew i think
and it's not even speculative because i
think i've witnessed this
i've witnessed a lot of people um
who who who are without any
yeah and you know like it's not i i
think i mean i
i agree that i think we can only have
perhaps a handful
uh of those kinds of friends because of
because of how
because of how much air they take sort
of absolutely
isn't it they have very
that's just so tragic that's the suicide
of of being um it is oh that's a that's
a great way of putting it that's exactly
i think that's true when you abandon all
friends and you're just this
you know ship adrift somewhere you know
before
you know watching your your computer
screen and
i think that goes back to chris's point
about the person that you stake
you know uh your life against their
death
against their despair i i just finished
reading with a good friend of mine dan
shapi
the plague by camus and you know
and running through it i mean you know
the character
uh he told me the character he
identified me with and then
he was reading ahead of me and i sort of
accepted it intentionalized me with
tarot and teru's project i've been
talking
i've sort of seen that it's my way of
calling my project teru's thing is he
wants to learn how to be a saint without
god
um and and that that that's literally
the phrase he uses
but what you see in the plague and the
plague of course is this i mean it's
i think it's the book that helped can we
win the nobel prize right
it's a beautiful book masterpiece um in
some ways i think it's a better book
than the stranger
um but in the plague the plague of
course there's a
fred it's so apropos right now there's a
french town it
it's uh overwhelmed by plague they lock
down they go into quarantine etc
and of course it's a metaphor for human
beings confronting absurdity and
mortality and that
and that but what what you see in it is
exactly that you see that you see the
friendships
the friendships between like ryu and
teru
and some of the other the friendship is
the thing that
it's amazing because camus writes it so
beautifully he
he doesn't write it romantically he
doesn't he all
but what he shows he shows that the
friendships
that's the locus that which calls
to us and calls calls to us from
another's depth
and calls to us from our depth in a way
that preserves our humanity against
whatever
i mean this sounds trite but against
whatever the universe can sort of throw
at it i mean that that's the point
like when i when i hear about uh you
know
some of the friendships that were
maintained uh
in some of the deepest darkest
situations like you know you know in pow
camps and things like that
and how those friendships like
helped people preserve their humanity
when nothing else does
heroic individualism and all that stuff
that that all gets broken that all gets
broken
but the one thing uh that undermines it
the one thing that is not undermined is
friendship
it's it's telling that in 1984
um orwell gets this because what he does
the most horrific thing he does is he
ultimately undermines the relationship
and the friendship between winston and
julia
and that's when they lose their soul
that's when they lose their soul
[Music]
yeah that's when he loves big brother um
yeah he loves the it
instead of the vow he's he's right he
loses and that's the whole point of the
party
if you if you read the book you realize
the whole point of the party is to
absolutely destroy the possibility of
friendship and fellowship
so that the only thing that's left is
the devotion to big brother
and the market and the state are trying
to do that
right now and that's what you're
pointing to andrew that's what you're
pointing to
yeah it also occurs to me that i i had a
couple thoughts while you were talking
one is that
um that you know this kind of friendship
is is not necessarily
um temporal like you could have friends
from books or you could have friends
that are that that
have passed away or that you no longer
talk to or you know uh you can cultivate
friends
in all kinds of places that you could be
alone and maybe
at times solitude is more of a place to
cultivate
a generous uh genuine friendship than
you know in the crowd um
yeah i think that's a really good point
and also that it
it also seems that um
there is a certain
there's something about those kinds of
friendships that are also both voluntary
and
involuntary simultaneously i think that
it's important to understand that too
it's frank's first it's frank's first uh
voluntary necessity
volunteering necessity was always a
that's right that's right you enter into
it you find that
uh you couldn't you couldn't be without
it right
because then suddenly suddenly you live
in a world in which it is presupposed
yes exactly and and once you live in a
world in which that friendship is
presupposed
it cannot be discarded right because it
becomes like it becomes a fundament of
your being
as such i use those terms deliberately
right
you're being as such begins to depend
upon it and
and it's not something that you can
hasten into you can't rush into it and
you also can't contrive it
that's the other thing i think sometimes
people think you know there's something
formulaic about people when they have
convergent interests and perhaps
personalities that would seem bios by
all psychometric criteria to be
compatible
and you know what sometimes it just does
not work and that does that's not to
romanticize it necessarily but there is
something
there is and must be deep mystery within
the emergence of authentic friendship
some some of it has to remain mysterious
must always remain mysterious
i like that um i like the fact that
you're pointing out the involuntary
aspect of it the fact
that's why you fall in love and this i
wonder if you
fall in love that that's actually philia
and not eros in the sense that you
on some level because because you you
develop a bond with a person
a creative bond with the person that
that that endures through time and it's
not merely uh
you know an erotic thing it's it's
something
it develops more from aeros into philia
or or something like that are you
following my
yeah well plato came out yes talks about
a shift in it within eros itself
he talks about like there's there's a
kind of eros that's the consumptive eros
so right you want it you you want to be
one with something in and you consume it
yeah right and then he talks about the
pack that it you can it could flip
and you can get this move where eros
goes from being consumptive
eras to being generative eras and he
says when we
and he he gives a prototypical example
of encountering beauty
and wanting to make more beauty you
don't want to consume the beauty so it
disappears into you
that's not the direction the direction
is the other way you want to make more
beauty in response to the beauty you've
seen
and then he indicates that that is
preparing you for
right the philia in the socratic
relationship yeah and that's why you
could be married for a long time right
you because it's because you keep going
with that creation of beauty you don't
it doesn't end somewhere
uh along the way i'm sorry i just i was
just thinking that you know
that the the essence of the husband-wife
relationship
right is is really is really about that
is you know we're talking about
friendship
but it's also the essence of the
husband-and-wife relationship and
i i think cause you say your wife is
your best friend or or that and
and the reason you don't leave this
person because there's so many other
options
is because you've you've gone beyond
that state
where you can continue to to
continue to to create this beauty that
you're talking about or
which isn't necessarily something so
tangible or
and it's also a unique language as we've
been talking about right
i think i think so i think the spousal
relationship is
different from friendship not because of
absence but but because of excess
i think the spousal relationship should
have all three loves
um uh at least the generative form of
eros
definitely philia in both the friendship
and fellowship sense
but also agape um uh there's a sense in
which you're helping
you're helping to midwife you're helping
to give birth to that person's
uh aspirational self there's a sense in
which you're
you're taking you're doing you're
engaged in the love of creativity
uh and of course the problem with that
with an adult
right is to not do that in any way
that's patronizing or condescending
so it's precisely i think the eros
and the philia that counterbalance that
you know
that pretentious patronizing aspect
danger at least of agape but i think
it's also agape
that makes sure that the eros doesn't
become consumptive
and i think what is mediating between
all of them and keeping them going
like you said andrew is philia and
and so if you look at sort of the
measures of long-term relationship
yeah the phyllis team tends to be
central
but especially for long-term
relationships there's a
gothic element into it like chris said
you
you the gothic element is you help
like you're a world through which the
other you give birth to a world
to which the other person can come into
who and what they are
that or or to use it another way andrew
you there's an agape in creation elect
creating a unique language
by which that other person can come into
articulation
um so i think i think all of them i i
i hesitate to speak like i have any
authority about this because
i mean i mean i'm in such a relationship
now but uh
trying to get uh relationships to last a
lifetime is not something yet i've
succeeded in
so i have to bow to your expertise on
this uh but oh no
from what i've seen and from what i've
observed and from what i
have good reason to believe i'm now
participating in
and and from the research i've looked at
this i think if you have all three
and they shift around in what is
prominent at any one stage in the
relationship
right you know you know there's periods
where um the erotic aspect can come to
the fore or the friendship aspect
or the agothic aspect sure yeah
yeah i mean i think again again it the
degree to which
if that argument is right and they're
interpenetrating the degree to which we
have denuded
right and diminished friendship is the
degree to which
the other two are also denuded and
diminished
and and the way they all relate to each
other is also denuded
and diminished i think it's no
coincidence that the people that only
have
you know facebook friends have a
tremendous difficulty
having committed romantic relationships
that's not a coincidence
that's not a coincidence at all yeah
yeah there's also something kind of
interesting in the um
incidentally before i say this you know
all of all of this serves to
um
serves to depict what is at stake
in the loss of friendship you know
um i know for myself the
the um the quaking of that foundation
the prospect of the loss of a friendship
of that nature
and of that intensity i can't i can't
speak to the spousal relationship but
if i can return it momentarily to the
philia of friendship
the loss of which to me is such a it
brings a kind of existential
stress that in my experience very very
few things can compare
um because when you're
you know when you're when you're
when your life begins to presuppose that
foundation
and begins to presuppose the
reproduction from the worlds that are
opened by those
friendships the risk of the loss of
those worlds is tantamount to the risk
of the loss of soul to bring it back to
despair for a moment
it's funny and that's why it is such a
seismic
threat at least in my mind an experience
when you know even if there's no real
imminent threat of the loss thereof if
there's even a sort of a real
disruption to the foundation of those
worlds
the um i think the consequences
the the existential consequences of that
and the follow-up from that can be
incredibly pernicious
and deleterious to the living of to the
lived life and
understanding though and understanding
those stakes i think is very very
important to the treatment of those
friendships
you know because it helps to make sure
that in treating those friendships you
are not treating them
as mere you know what we're treating
them duly as
the worlds they are and um
and and and often you know sometimes too
friendships to take your point about the
consumptive eras john and how you know
the concept
the difference between the consent of
eros and the generative eras
that very difference often is
is is is the difference that makes for a
barren
world or a fruitful world
in the soil of that friendship you know
i've i've hit moments in my life where
i've realized
that a friend whom i cherished very
deeply
was in fact my what was what was
driving my the need i had that drove
my pursuit of that friendship was of a
consumptive erotic nature and of course
i mean erotic in the broader sense not
in the sexual sense right
but there was a there was a consumptive
eros that was actually an unconscious
determinant
of the relevance of that friendship to
me yeah
i'm sure yeah we i know we many of us
that experience isn't that interesting
like everybody goes through that
you have to you have to threshold that
you have to go through and
yes i discovered this poem i wrote a
long time ago for a woman
and it was just this barrage of sex and
death and and you know every kind of
melodrama you can even imagine it was
just it was just like
pouring out of my unconsciousness you
know we all go
through that right and then and then
it's like the romantic has to die or
something
i don't know that's right that's right
it's like that need you know whatever it
is that that consumptive erotic need
that can sometimes
move friendships with a force that goes
unseen to you has to be made opaque it
has right it's the transparency opacity
shift that has to happen you have to
become conscious and aware
that's why it's meiotic and sometimes
you have to become conscious of the
nature of your need
and how rapacious it is and then and
then sometimes in so doing
it's almost like a sacramental process
in so doing
a friendship and the and the
potential of a friendship can be renewed
in that process it doesn't necessarily
mean the death of a friendship
it can actually mean the renewal of a
friendship and the reopening of the
friendship
back into the the motive i thou and
and when that happens i find especially
if it's requited
it is such a profound experience yeah
and i was thinking that friendship is
also in stages like
like when you were talking i thought of
like
the period when you when when things
become translucent or transparent is
when you become an adult
on some level so yeah it's like it's
like becoming a mature friend
um there there's there's there's a
there's a there's an evolution to
friendship it's not it's not a
thing yes i was thinking chris as you
were talking
i was thinking about because we often uh
we've talked about
the the mythos around these perennial
patterns
i was thinking about the vampire myth as
opposed to the
like the zombie myth is the myth of uh
you know what we've argued
with with philip the myth of the meaning
crisis
but the the vampire myth strikes me as a
as a really appropriate myth
of especially because of all the
perversions of christian fellowship
that are within uh the vampire because
the vampire is
someone who sucks the life out of you uh
right and
and the consumptive hunger is is
insatiable
um not in the same way not in the
mindless way of the zombie
but in the way in which i it is i mean
vampires are sort of the the
quintessential narcissists
right that everything is drawn and
that's why they literally have the power
of drawing attention
right you know you know the bella legusi
example is famous for that
and then i wonder if that's the case
that the vampire
represents how we can
deeply betray by leah
the fact that we have gone through this
cultural movement of
making the vampire sexy and fun
isn't that maybe a way in which our
culture
is unconsciously indicating
what we've been talking about here that
it has lost
the understanding of friendship because
it's lost the horror of the vampire
the vet being a vampire is cool you get
to live for a long time
and all that right and it's like no you
don't understand it yeah
the vampires are all 20 somethings now
which is sort of the
the age of narcissism right when yeah
when 20s you're kind of like
you're self-obsessed you haven't learned
to you know develop me
you know you haven't you haven't had
enough relationships to
to know what it means to i don't know
develop
i mean not always a good point that's a
very good point andrew i hadn't thought
about that that's even in one of those
horrible books by ann
rice but the idea of the perpetual the
the the immortality is also a perpetual
immaturity
the vampires yeah the the sorry what did
you say chris
forever young the forever young yeah
yeah the
vampire so maybe the the little prince
or the the peter pan myth and the
vampire myth they're they're coming
together right
yeah yeah yeah adolescent and uh
and the forever young pairing the
forever young with the living death is a
very
it's an interesting pairing john yeah
yeah it's it's it's
definitely um sells a lot of you know
tv shows and so and the and and then the
so the youth obsession of our culture
and the trivialization
that han talks about so much in the
agony of eras
and the scent of time and saving beauty
i mean right all
all of that the perpetual immaturity of
our culture
that then that would also feed into your
point andrew
and also help another loop explaining
why
friendship is so radically
trivialized in our culture because
because
the 20-something is supposed to be when
you're moving from
buddies to the real possibility of
friendship
but if you're always in that liminal
place and if you're always
what you're trying to do is get whatever
you can from it the vampire
then then of course you're going to be
perpetually
incapable of friendship that and that's
that's a really horrific thought
what would it be like what would it be
like to be
psychologically set your character is so
malformed
that real friendship the friendship that
creates these what we said this unique
language
where we're not just communicating where
we're communing with each other
what would it be like to not be capable
of that
what would that be like i mean i i don't
i don't know what that kind of but i
think it's a kind of perennial
starvation
like that's how i think about it you
know
sorry andrew i didn't know i said it's a
living death it's it's it's it's you're
one of the undead the
uh you know really because
there's just nothing it's your whole
movie your life is a friend's
sitcom it's like it's horror you know
yeah be because it's your your
i think of the image of uh i think of
the image of of um
i think of the satanic image at the at
the bottom of dante's inferno
right right the flapping of the wings
right the the
the um the the striving but the modally
confused
striving is precisely what recreates the
conditions
of incarceration right as he flaps his
wings
he cools the world and keeps himself
encased in ice
and i think that that state is something
akin to that it's like the very
the kind of the kind of the consumptive
and rapacious
form of eros that drives people to want
to collect and consume one another is
the very thing
that keeps them perennially fixed and
and mo
and motionless really insofar as they
just they can't
incapable of the kind of
self-transcendence that would have them
again
know and be known prop in proper
reciprocity with another person
so that knowing and being no i mean
that's the deep relationship then
between philia
dialogos and the cultivation of wisdom
right if you can't enter into
philia if you can't commune then you're
not going to have deal logos you're not
going to have these conversations that
take on a life of their own
and give birth to new ways of seeing and
being and without that
then the possibility of knowing yourself
virtuously because
when you know yourself to know yourself
virtually
like chris i think you even made this
pun in one of the things you wrote
to know yourself virtuously is to know
yourself in virtue of others
right there's there's there's there's a
inherent binding there together
and so without i mean
so without phylia there's no dear logos
and there is no capacity
for that kind of knowledge the
self-knowledge that makes us wise
so instead so what so what you do then
yes right you gather
you gather the likes you gather the
connections and you don't have any
aspirational self-knowledge you don't
have any
socratic self-knowledge you fill it up
with narcissistic
autobiography because that hole there is
also missing
and so what you do is you're posting all
the pictures right and you're doing all
the things on instagram
and you're constantly yeah it's sort of
attention economy
yes exactly and all you're doing is
constantly running the autobiography
yes yes yes yes except the autobiography
remains literal autobiography
because one of the things and as opposed
to you know you know what that
so you know how when you have a when you
have a friendship an authentic
friendship that you have you've had for
a very long time
shared autobiography becomes a way
or shared memory if i can put it that
way using it in the augustinian sense of
memory yeah
yeah memory the memory becomes a world
in which to play through
the mem the shared memory the commons of
the shared memory
becomes a world in which to
to to make yourselves more mutually
known
rather than simply to trace over
journeys undertaken the tracing over
journeys undertaken
actually becomes a way of co-mapping
your your sort of expanding
reference for one another yeah do you
know what i mean i'm
struggling to get this one out a little
bit but that the and i guess what i'm
trying to say is
that the the reliving of shared memory
has to be a symbolic exercise rather
than
a literal exercise totally it's it's the
memory of satie
it's not the memory of uh of chronology
it's the it's the memory that brings
mindfulness of the deep
remembering of who and what we can be
it's an ontological remember it's an
ontological memory
historical remembering that's right it's
the it's it's the vertical
it's yeah exactly it's vertical that's
why that's right
you know opus was was all about really
wasn't it it was it was
it was you know writing down in my new
detail
the the beingness that he had
experienced in his life and
transforming that um yeah
transforming that in into meaning and
instead of triviality or or
you know yeah you're talking about the
remembrance of this there are
lots of things past yeah yeah i think
that's exactly right andrew i think
that's exactly right
i think which is why it's such a
profound novel right yeah
exactly it's almost like a parable
uh parables are things that look like
narratives but actually undermine
narrative from within
right uh so because what they do is they
they they they they they dislodge you
from that horizontal
autobiography and they set you into the
ontology so like the parable of the
prodigal son is
right it like i said this before that
there's that that there's the tension
between justice and
compassion and and and between the
father
the role of the father and the role of
the elder son and the role of the
younger son and if you try to resolve it
in terms
of any one of these things in favor of
any one of them you lose your humanity
while justice should always plan no
compassion should always plan
no the father should always teach no the
elder son should
no the point is and that's what jesus is
doing and he said and then he says
he does the typical jesus thing and the
kingdom of god is like this and you go
oh my
oh right so you get this right but
proust is like that too because what
happens is
you you you know swansway and all this
you're reading
what sounds like an autobiography but
but but you realize like you said andrew
you you realize no no wait the bottom
drops out and i'm not really moving this
way
i'm moving this way i'm right like he's
exploring the depths of humanity
i had a similar experience when i read
um the great gatsby
right um i'm reading the great gatsby
and i'm reading this book and i'm kind
of frustrated with it i'm going along
and i'm saying what is it why is this
book famous yeah you do
like i thought it was kind of boring
it's like here's the story
this love story is like is this this
audible it's just this bio these
biographies unfolding
about these indulgent people and then
you get to the last five pages of the
book and it goes
and you go oh my gosh he hasn't been
talking about these people at all
he's been talking about the american
dream and he's been talking about the
collapse of the american dream and the
corrupting us
and and you get that you get that drop
into the vertical
uh-huh drop into the vertical yeah yeah
well and so
here's another pithy way of putting it
friends our ways
they share and they afford the dropping
into the vertical for each other
yeah yes yes which is why they're i was
gonna say one of the things i wrote down
was that
if there's a risk involved in friendship
because you can you can lose a friend
like it's a
and also a friendship a friend is as is
is not something that
it's not a smooth operation to use on
language it's something that challenges
you
yeah they're very deep it's a labor it's
a labor to go back to the midwifery
metaphor it's a labor
and so so so i guess that's why it's
sacred again but
i guess that's why it's also a a journey
and i guess that's why it's also hard
difficult you know it's it's a tr it can
be a trial uh
sometimes well every relationship
every relationship ends in loss right
every
i mean you know every relationship ends
in law and and this is where
you know you if you take a look at uh
because i've been teaching all of them
recently
you know epicurean the epic we our
understanding of epicureanism is is
totally off
epicureanism it's about you know
philosophical contemplative
companionship that's what epic
that's at the heart of epicureanism and
then of course uh you know
and then of course within stoicism as
well
and they both they're both they both
venerate friendship
profoundly and deeply but they always do
it
in the recognition that's what i meant
about that's why i was invoking camus
the plague
because every relationship ends in loss
either the relationship
is betrayed or damaged irreparably or
the person dies
right and and and so the stoics the
stoics actually
the the pre-meditation you're always
supposed to remind yourself sati
that eat every friendship um every
friendship is is is subject to fatality
in that way everything even your even
relation even relationship to objects
um but the point is not to stop because
of it
right the point the point is not to say
well i'm not
the point is not uh you know i'm going
to pack up my toy my emotional toys and
go home
the point is not it's the is is
precisely the opposite
it's to see go ahead oh i'm just
thinking that the opposite is also true
is this the friend remains with you
always
until you die you know if it's a deep
friendship it
never leaves so it's both those things
are true yes
they are they are and that and that's
the point and even if you have an
antagonistic religion relationship with
this person
and you break up or you they they're
still working inside of you on some
level and they're still having their
effect on you you can't
you can't get you can't escape from from
a from a real friend i don't think i
think there's no no you can't you can't
and actually it's that's almost very
crucial
it's almost very crucial to the real
friendship because the responsibility is
is there
whether you decide to take it up or not
right i i i think i it's been my
experience
that once you love somebody and love not
lost or acquaintance or
care once you love somebody you always
love them to some degree
yeah i mean so i mean
and even in grief whether it's the grief
of rejection or the grief of loss
right you you still love the person but
it's interesting you the the the whole
if you didn't love them it wouldn't hurt
right that's the point and also you you
might even you hate them as well
and some people like you might have hate
for them what you know and how they
how what happened you might yeah but
that doesn't take that away
either i mean so the interesting thing
about it is
uh um so
what i what what i was going to say
nothing
you interrupted me andrews is hey guys
sorry angie you dropped out for a second
i had
i had a bit of a latency problem uh the
last thing i heard you say was jordan
peterson
okay so let me make the point i said
invoking jordan peterson's like
invoking voldemort
he made a point and i it's not his
insight but he made it famous
that meaning what i would call meaning
in life is what sustains you when you're
not happy
when you're not cheerful when you're not
content um
and what i was what i was suggesting was
that friendship is the tutorial
for that friendship is where we get the
lived sense
of it being worth it even though there
is going to be
loss even though there is going to be
conflict we get a deep
and so in the epicureans and the stoics
you get
the sense of friendship as where you get
and i want to break this word up to
emphasize it where you get
encouragement where because courage
isn't just fortitude
courage is a sense of the meaning of
life that sustains you
even when things are going horribly and
friendship is the place
where the stoics and especially the
epicureans
thought we practiced that we thought
well and you have something similar in
buddhism andrew
you have the buddha and the dharma need
the sangha
and so i think that the degree
also which and you have the spiritual
friend i think it's called
which who is who you you can't really go
very far without that yeah
you can't and that's what you see also
again in the plague
and so again i think and we don't talk
enough
about this verge virtue i mean we've
we've fallen
into a maniacal monologue about justice
not even internal justice
just social justice social justice is
important it really is
but justice and soccerson have to be
talked about and so does courage
and degree to which people are not
capable
i'm going to make a prediction here
something i think we could actually test
i think the degree to which people are
incapable of
friendship of a communing relationship
that we've the time we've been talking
about here
is the degree to which they are not
going to get practice in
existential encouragement the courage to
be
the defense against despair and
therefore the existential cowards
that's a prediction i'm going to make
yeah or the degree to which they're
merciful on some level right
i mean um but but those go together
cowardice and cruelty powers and cruelty
are deeply interwoven and bound together
yeah
they're deep you cruelty always comes
out of
tremendous insecurity that's why you see
the cruelty of people like trump
it's because he is such a fundamental
coward
right that's why he that's also why he's
incapable of real friendship
right that's why you see the cruelty
that he sort of
espouses without giving it a second
thought uh because those are bound
together insecurity
and cowardice and right and cruelty are
always bound together
yeah well it just occurred to me that
justice right
uh this idea of justice without the
sense
of without that sense of understanding
what fruit what philia and friendship is
about
would lead you to be unmerciful and and
cruel and
and and shallow and and you know
so it's you know there was a song by
three dog night
which which really dates me really
probably chris doesn't even know who i'm
talking about but you do andrew
well there was a song called you know uh
it's
you know it's easy to be hard and then
they're actually lying in here about you
know people who care about
uh justice but but in the line is that
they care about justice but as you said
they're incapable of actual friendship
uh with each other
and i think i think the severing the
attempt to sever justice from fellowship
and even a sense of common wealth and
ideology becomes the substitute doesn't
it like uh
shared belief basically we just become
we've become propositional buddies
yeah we have a song and there's a
feminine venomous behind it and a
you know which which arises with it that
is you know it's where it
gets the where the where the scapegoat
thing
mechanism kind of comes into being where
or you want it i don't know you want to
join together with somebody and destroy
something rather than
join together with somebody and create
if that makes
yeah well it's just it's just group
vampires right it's like
it's like it's it's group vampires yeah
yeah the mob mentality kind of thing
um and and and we can mob together with
our words as much as we can mob together
with our actions
um and that's problematic that's why
again i think the myths
i mean there's a reason why there's a
reason why i think
i mean there's many mythic elements in
things like tolkien
but the fellowship of the ring is a myth
that's running all the way through
and i think the profound attraction for
that is for many people
it awakens and it helps them satie to
remember
how much they need friendship how much
they need it
yeah yeah yeah because friendship in and
of itself is like
it's like it's like um
within within the suffering of life
wow that's beautiful say that again
um friendship cocoons the memory of the
eternal
within the intrinsic suffering of life
that's that yeah that's it for that he
just sam and frodo on the mountain with
all this
you know that the world is collapsing
around them that seat yeah
but that's very beautiful yeah yeah
exactly that was beautifully said chris
well it was just
just taking all all that you two just
said and just trying to
synthesize it in a sense um
yeah yeah and that's why that's why
expressions of the
the sam and frodo example is so
canonical for a good reason
it's incredibly moving i i i've never
ceased to be moved by it for precisely
that reason because it's like a pure arc
it's like a pure distillation of that
insight and maybe that's that expression
maybe the harry potter books are sort of
the opposite
you know in a sense the friendships
there are all about
rebelling against the adult world or
something like that or maybe i'm wrong
i'm not an excellent i think there's
i think there is authentic friendship in
that story but i don't think that the
i don't think that the friendship is as
um is as central to the story
as it is in lord of the rings because
it's the because harry potter is a
messianic story
it's a messianic so it's the death and
resurrection of christ basically
that's that's essentially what harry
potter is and that's why it's so
it's so beloved because it's a very very
thinly disguised
um story of christ but i still wonder if
it's beloved for the wrong reasons
at times uh you know and it's in the way
that the
you know just the like what we're
talking about is these little groups of
people playing quidditch with each other
and they're sort of like that
it reflects the superficial aspect right
it doesn't have this
sacred quality yeah i think
there there's a i think chris's point is
the friendships aren't as pivotal
because it's
the story is about harry potter and how
he's a messianic figure
so it's basically jesus and his
disciples
whereas in whereas in the lord of the
rings the super
power of the hobbits is friendship
that's what people
don't get everybody else has fantastic
abilities
but the super power of the hobbits is
friendship it's friendship that time and
time
time and time again preserves them
against the temptation to evil
again it's their friendship and it's the
and the shire
right it's the it's that and the shire
isn't a nationalism
it's again that sense of fellowship
right and
and and and and yeah village
it's a village and it's it's yes exactly
what the the kind of communities
i think that we're sort of you know
trying to create
in the wake of the collapse of of
civilization right
yes yes the smart village book is about
right
yeah the smart villages uh future
thinkers the civilian of jordan hall
it's all about trying to get the that
back but
right the the idea is right what makes
the hobbits
the the the beings that have the
ultimate courage there's other heroic
figures
there's gandalf there's aragorn but the
only ones that have the courage to the
end
for me the scene is when sam
lifts frodo up because he can't walk
anymore
and he carries frodo too
right yeah into the it's the part it's
the defining
it's the define it's the fulcrum moment
of the entire story
i think yeah for a good reason yeah very
much
very much
and again it comes back to your point
chris he he lift
he literally bears frodo up against
despair
yes yeah
yeah wow i should head out guys
i think that's a good place to uh bring
it to an end
i think that's a very good image to
circle around to
um but my time is pretty much up yeah
well
thanks for taking the time i see you're
you got you're incredibly you know
active and busy with talking to a lot of
people and so i appreciate you taking
the time
but i want but but i want to do this
again andrew i find all of these
reinventio
sessions yeah and i'm going to rename
like i i put them out as reinventing
because i thought reinvention would just
kind of sound weird and people wouldn't
get it
but then people have been writing and
saying what do you mean reinvent you
can't reinvent these things
it's not right so it should be
reinventio so i'm gonna i'm gonna
re-brand our our discussion as
reinventio and uh um
i thought that maybe like because i
really love the subject of friendship
that the next thing
we could if we if we dared to talk about
you know
the erotic or or the aspect of
friendship in love another time or the
next time if
i'd be happy to take that yeah let's do
that there's so much more to say
about this yeah there's just there's an
endless amount of things to say i think
but i i would like to explore also the
proposal which has fallen off our
cultural table
but it goes back to perhaps jesus of
nazareth it's definitely paul it's
definitely
an augustine and an aquinas of love as a
virtue
i want to re i would like to really
explore that because
the idea we we like we have i was
talking about this
in the the sangha this morning right
how how much we have lost how much we
perverted the sense of the word passion
right we we do things with passion and
we use this word
not realizing that the word passion is
related to passive
and the greek word is pathe from which
we get pathetic passion is the opposite
of action
and we think somehow that the intensity
of feeling
is what keeps people committed we look
because what we're actually valuing
is people's ability to commit to an
arduous
or long-standing task you can't do
anything without passion
what they're saying is you need
commitment but the ancient idea is
but feelings are ephemeral no matter how
intense they are
right what what keeps people committed
is a
power for committing to the good which
is exactly what virtue is
virtue is the power of committing to the
good and
so to my mind i was comparing the
intensity of infatuation i use this as
an example
with what you were talking about earlier
uh uh andrew
the virtue of uh that that
that that empowers you and encourages
you
to stay in a long-term relationship and
that's not an intense feeling it's a
virtue
so i would like next time if possible to
talk about love as a virtue
love is a virtue sure sounds great and
uh that's
another thing to reinvent right at
passion yeah wow
love is a virtue because because because
it means
like so many of these things we're
living in a time of inversion where
the thing we think it means is actually
almost its opposite right
exactly exactly and you're right to note
that we and this is jonathan pajot's
uh point about we live in the we live in
the topsy-turvy world we live in clown
world we live in the upside down world
yeah
always predictive of the end of an epoch
and of a civilized
end of a civilization it it speaks of
of an imminent death on large scale when
all these things
all these things have gone through some
major inversion yeah i think
talking about love is a virtue and
talking about the inverting of
of it's almost like frodo and sam like
the end of all things
the inversion of all things let's talk
about both of those let's talk about
love is a virtue
and the inversion of all things and the
inversion of all things okay
i'll write it down here okay
very good oh well
thank you thank you so much i i love
these conversations
uh just to death it just uh yeah yep
exactly i think they're
i think they're life-giving exactly that
they certainly are
thank you andrew john of course um both
of you
yeah both of you guys good night then
take care bye bye